import 'package:vidhan/games/quize/models/question.dart';

const List<Question> questions = [
  Question(
    question: '1. What does Article 16 of the Indian Constitution guarantee?',
    correctAnswerIndex: 1,
    options: [
      'a) Right to equality before law',
      'b) Equality of opportunity in matters of public employment',
      'c) Right to freedom of speech',
      'd) Right to education',
    ],
  ),
  Question(
    question: '2. Which grounds are prohibited for discrimination under Article 16?',
    correctAnswerIndex: 0,
    options: [
      'a) Religion, race, caste, sex, descent, place of birth, and residence',
      'b) Age and disability',
      'c) Economic status',
      'd) All of the above',
    ],
  ),
  Question(
    question: '3. Article 16 applies to which of the following?',
    correctAnswerIndex: 1,
    options: [
      'a) Private employment only',
      'b) Public employment only',
      'c) Both private and public employment',
      'd) None of the above',
    ],
  ),
  Question(
    question: '4. Which clause of Article 16 allows for reservation in appointments for backward classes?',
    correctAnswerIndex: 2,
    options: [
      'a) Clause (1)',
      'b) Clause (2)',
      'c) Clause (4)',
      'd) Clause (5)',
    ],
  ),
  Question(
    question: '5. What is the significance of Article 16 in the context of social justice?',
    correctAnswerIndex: 1,
    options: [
      'a) It promotes unequal treatment in public services.',
      'b) It ensures equality and prevents discrimination in public employment.',
      'c) It allows for arbitrary appointments.',
      'd) It restricts employment opportunities for certain groups.',
    ],
  ),
  Question(
    question: '6. Can a law made by the State provide for special provisions for certain classes under Article 16?',
    correctAnswerIndex: 0,
    options: [
      'a) Yes, it can provide special provisions for backward classes.',
      'b) No, it cannot make any special provisions.',
      'c) Yes, but only for women.',
      'd) Yes, but only for minorities.',
    ],
  ),
  Question(
    question: '7. Which judicial case emphasized the importance of Article 16 regarding equal opportunity in public employment?',
    correctAnswerIndex: 1,
    options: [
      'a) Maneka Gandhi v. Union of India',
      'b) Indira Sawhney v. Union of India',
      'c) Kesavananda Bharati v. State of Kerala',
      'd) Minerva Mills v. Union of India',
    ],
  ),
  
  Question(
    question: '8. Which article complements Article 16 by prohibiting discrimination in matters of employment?',
    correctAnswerIndex: 0,
    options: [
      'a) Article 15',
      'b) Article 14',
      'c) Article 17',
      'd) Article 18',
   ],
   ),

   Question(
     question: "9. What does Article 16(3) allow?",
     correctAnswerIndex:1,
     options:[
        "a ) Special provisions for women",
        "b ) Special provisions for residents of a state",
        "c ) Special provisions for Scheduled Castes",
        "d ) Special provisions for foreign nationals",
     ],
   ),

   Question(
     question: "10. Which clause in Article 16 allows Parliament to make laws regarding the appointment and conditions of service of persons serving in connection with the affairs of the Union or any State?",
     correctAnswerIndex:2,
     options:[
        "a ) Clause (1)",
        "b ) Clause (2)",
        "c ) Clause (5)",
        "d ) Clause (4)",
     ],
   ),
];